CHRISTOPHER ORTIZ

DATA SCIENTIST

CONTACT INFORMATION

Phone: (210) 885-6635

Email: christopher.logan.ortiz@gmail.com

LinkedIn: christopherlortiz

Github: Promeos

PROFILE SUMMARY

I'm a self-motivated servant leader and Data Scientist with six years of award-winning customer service. I've had the honor to serve new hires as a trainer, mentor, and friend. Coupled with an education in finance and wealth management, I produce data-driven stories that generate insight and empower my audience.

SKILLS & EXPERTISE

- · Python Programming
- · SQL and Database Design
- Tableau
- Trello
- Applied Statistics
- · Machine Learning
- · Web Scraping
- · Distributed Processing
- · Natural Language Processing
- · Audit and Compliance
- Training & Coaching
- Texas Notary

ACADEMIC BACKGROUND

DATACAMP

Data Science | 2021 - Ongoing

Python Programmer Data Scientist with Python Data Analyst with SQL Server

CODEUP

Data Science | 2021

Fully immersive, project-based 22-week career accelerator that provides students with 670+ hours of expert instruction in applied data science.

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

Finance | 2016

Student Managed Investment Fund Equities Analyst and Investment Policy Compliance Officer.

DATA SCIENCE PROJECTS

SMART SAN ANTONIO

June 2021 - Ongoing

Using data provided by the City of San Antonio, I created a Tableau dashboard to provide stakeholders insight into the city's Street Light Pilot Program. The goal of the program is to test smart streetlights for their cost-effectiveness, feasibility, and benefit to the public. If the streetlight pilot is successful, CPS-Energy and the City of San Antonio will determine the possibility of scaling the solutions city-wide.

THE WORLD BANK SOL DATABASE

May 2021 - Ongoing

Using data provided by the World Bank, I created a SQL database of contracts and humanitarian projects approved by the World Bank. MySQL and T-SQL.

STELLAR CLASSIFICATION

May 2021

Using data provided by NASA, I predicted a star's class with 100% accuracy using a Decision Tree Classifier Model. The model outperformed the baseline by 500%. To build this model, I conducted Two-Tailed T-Tests, ANOVA, and Chi-Squared tests and determined that a star's radius (size) and absolute magnitude (brightness) are drivers of a star's class. The model can be used with Transit Photometry to find star systems that could sustain human life.

JOBLY

January 2021 - April 2021

Created an online dashboard that connects job seekers with the skills they need to become a Data Scientist or Web Developer. I automated data acquisition and preparation (ETL) using python and cron and stored the prepared dataset in an AWS S3 Bucket.

WORK EXPERIENCE

SENIOR TELLER

Credit Human | 2018-2020

Trained and led a team of bank tellers daily. Created branch cash usage reports and audited new products and services. Reduced excess cash on hand by 28% to meet compliance guidelines by creating an easy-to-use Excel Spreadsheet.

DEPARTMENT TRAINER

Amazon | 2016-2018

Trained new employees on safety etiquette, proper equipment use and maintenance, and problem resolution skills. Audited and coached employees. Evaluated the daily performance of the department and presented my analysis to management.